Hey, guys.
Welcome to our last
lecture of this quarter.
And we're very happy
to have Douwe here.
He's the CEO of Contextual AI,
the enterprise LLM company,
as well as an adjunct
professor in symbolic systems
here at Stanford.
And previously, he was the head
of research at Hugging Face;
and before that, a research
scientist at Facebook AI
Research.
He received his PhD and master's
from the University of Cambridge
as well as a master's in
logic from the University
of Amsterdam and studied
philosophy and cognitive
AI in undergrad.
And his work focuses on machine
learning, as well as NLP,
specifically on developing
better models for language
understanding and generation,
and better tools for evaluation
and management.
OK, I give it up for Douwe.
All right.
Thank you.
So I guess I have to
stand here in the corner
so people can see me
on the Zoom as well.
Yeah, thanks so much
for having me here.
So I asked Stephen what
I should talk about.
There were a couple of things I
could talk about-- multimodality
or evaluation.
And this was the
preferred topic, I guess,
because the others
were already covered.
So yeah, I'm very happy to
talk to you about everything
retrieval augmentation.
I think this is really
one of the coolest topics
right now in our field.
So I'll just give
you an overview
of what's been
happening and what
I think are the interesting
questions to think about.
So first of all, obviously,
in case you've missed it,
we are in the age
of language models.
And I just wanted to
do a quick poll here
in this not super big audience.
I guess there's more
people on the Zoom.
But who invented
language models?
If you thought OpenAI,
then I'm angry with you.
So actually, this is
a very, very old idea.
So the idea is just
you take a sequence,
and you vectorize out
the token probabilities.
And so it wasn't
invented by OpenAI.
It's not like a few years old.
It's actually
several decades' old.
So I'm bringing this up because
I was talking to someone,
and they were like OpenAI
invented language models.
And I was like, you're
kidding me, right?
So I went back to
the literature.
And this is the oldest one
I could find, actually.
1991, first neural
language model.
There's a very nice paper
from 2003 from Bengio,
where they actually have word
embeddings and everything
already in there.
So, obviously, these
are LMs, not LLMs.
And as it turns out, if
you make them really big
and you parameterize them with
these massive neural nets,
then you get something
really powerful
that really shows
emergent properties.
And that's why we're all
so excited in this stuff.
So if we think about this
from a classic CS perspective,
there's input/output.
There's this thing
in the middle.
It's the generator.
So we take a sequence,
the input sequence.
And then the task of the model
is to predict the next token.
Very, very simple model.
And so that's why it was so easy
to come up with this in 1991
already, because the
idea is very intuitive.
But for a long time, what
was really broken with
this was the user interface.
And this, I think,
a lot of people
misunderstand what
ChatGPT was about.
That's really what
ChatGPT fixed.
So initially, you had to come
up with these very weird prompts
in order to get
your language model
to do what you wanted it to do.
And humans are terrible at this.
So we're much better at telling
people or things around us
what we want.
So if we have a dog, we say sit.
We don't prompt it in a very
weird way so that it sits.
And it's the same with
the language model.
If you wanted to
generate some rap
lyrics in the style of a pirate
or Shakespeare or something,
then you tell it,
generate some rap
lyrics in the style of pirates.
So that kind of
instruction data actually
turns out to be super,
super rare in just web data.
So what you need to do is you
need to fix the user interface
to the language model.
And the classic recipe for doing
that is the sequence basically
the ChatGPT used.
So you prompt the model
in a specific way.
You instruction
fine tune the model,
and you do some alignment RLHF,
whatever you do on top of that.
So that's the first thing.
So now you have a
working language model
with a working user interface.
So are we done then?
Obviously, we're not.
So right now, language models
are taking the world by storm.
But if you talk to anyone,
especially in an enterprise,
for example, where they
have very strict accuracy
requirements, they will tell
you that they can't really
productionize this yet.
And the reason is because there
are all these familiar problems.
Probably a bunch of you are
working on these problems
right now around hallucination.
So these models,
they make up stuff
very often with very
high confidence, which
is even more scary in a way.
Attribution-- so we don't
really know why these models
are saying what they're saying.
Stillness-- they go out of date.
So this was a big
problem with ChatGPT
not knowing anything that
happened after a certain cutoff
date.
And they keep updating
it every once in a while.
But you want to
have a system that's
always completely up to
date, that never goes stale.
You want to be able to revise
the information in the system.
So if you're a
European organization,
you have to worry
about GDPR, which
means that you need to be
able to remove information
from the language model or
maybe revise facts, which
we don't really know how to do.
So again, this is a
very interesting area
of study for a lot of
folks model editing.
So this is something that we
really want to be able to fix.
And then there's
this big question of,
how do you customize
these models?
So different people have
different use cases.
You have different data.
If you're a company
or if you want
to have a language
model on your own data,
how do you make it
work on your own data?
So one of the solutions
that everybody
has started using right
now is to couple it
to an external memory.
So that's really just RAG.
So we can-- this whole lecture
is basically about RAG.
But the way to understand
what is going on here
is we have a generator
just like before.
We have the input and a
prompt just like before.
But now, instead of just
giving those two things,
we give this additional context.
So we contextualize the language
model using things we retrieved.
And the retriever is
very often pretty simple.
It's just a query and
a document encoder.
And then you get a
bunch of documents.
You give them as context
through the model.
So super simple architecture.
And I think it's useful
to think about it
from the perspective of
these two separate paradigms.
So if you've ever
taken an exam--
I'm sure you have--
you can have a closed
book exam, where
you have to memorize
all of this or you
have to cram all the knowledge
into your parameters,
your neurons.
Or you have an open
book exam, where
you have all of this
information in the book
that you can access
when you do the exam.
So it's a very similar
thing with RAG.
You can just make it an open
book setting where you give it
access to this external
information Wikipedia
or something else or
basically the entire internet
and then have the
language model do
its job without having
to memorize all of it
in its parameters.
So the other, I think,
useful distinction
here is that cramming everything
into your parameters, that's
the parametric approach.
So what we're doing
with RAG is we're
adding this non-parametric
retrieval component.
So you might call
this semi-parametric
if you want to give this a name.
All right, so why does that
actually solve these issues?
And so the answer is
basically that if you
have this separate index,
this separate retriever,
you can swap it in.
You can swap it out.
You can replace it
with a new index
so you can really customize it.
And so you can customize
your language model system
for what the user
really wants to see.
And then, obviously, you
can update this index.
So it doesn't really
go stale, and you
can revise it if everything goes
wrong-- if anything goes wrong.
The other thing you
get is grounding.
So that's initially
why I became interested
in this kind of
architecture, because I
was thinking a lot about
grounding and multimodality
and things like that.
And actually, one really
nice way to ground things
is to find some other
information that you
can ground your generation in.
So you really want the language
model to only say things
that it has evidence for
in this other piece of text
or even multimodal data that
it retrieves separately.
So if you do that, then
you get less hallucination,
because you can always
point back to your source.
It's always grounded
in your source.
And you get
attribution because you
know why the model is
saying what it's saying
is because it found
that this thing here.
Is that clear?
All right, so for the
rest of this lecture,
we're going to talk about
this basic architecture.
And so it kind looks like
a pretty simple thing,
but there are
actually lots and lots
of questions you can ask about
what this system should really
look like.
And this doesn't even cover
half the questions you can ask.
So it really is about how do
we optimize this entire system.
So we have these
separate components--
the retriever, the generator.
And then there are things
like this query encoder.
How do we encode queries?
How do we do the retrieval?
Do we update the
document encoder?
How do we actually
define the document?
Is it like a full
document, or is
it a paragraph or a chunk or a
sentence or a couple of words?
So there are lots
of questions to ask.
And as you'll see, there
are lots of possible answers
to these questions as well.
So this is what we'll cover.
So there are lots
of architectures
going into these questions.
And I think as we go through
them, it's useful for you
to think about what happens
during training time
and what happens
during test time.
So during training time,
it's really, OK, we
have this language model.
We have this retriever.
Which one do we update?
How do we update them?
How do we train
this entire system?
Do we maybe not train it at all?
Do we pre-train it from scratch?
Do we initialize it with
components that were already
separately trained?
These are the kinds
of questions that you
have to answer if you want
to design a system like this.
And then during test time,
you have this entire system.
So actually multiple models in
a way that are working together.
So there's also different
things you can do there.
So give it different
indices during test time
or manipulate how you're
sampling, things like that.
So the starting point
for all of this stuff,
I think if you ask someone
now, like, What is RAG?
they will think of this thing.
So this is frozen
RAG, basically.
There's no training here at all.
So going back to this question
of train time, test time,
there's only test time here.
Train time happens separately
with these black box
models that we don't
necessarily have control over.
So there's this
document embedding model
is whatever is
currently at the top
of some open-source leaderboard.
You use that-- oops, sorry--
to get some vectors
that you then use
to create this vector database.
And then the vector
database just does search.
And it gives the information
from the search to the language
model.
And it just passes
it as the context.
So this only works because
of in-context learning.
And I think as a
machine learner myself,
this feels very inelegant.
So what this
lecture is about is,
can we do better than
this frozen thing?
So let's start from
the left side of this.
OK, if we want to outperform
this frozen thing itself
with just the vector
database, what
would that look like from
a retrieval perspective?
And the starting point for
everything retrieval is TF-IDF.
Does everybody know
what TF-IDF is?
No?
OK, so TF-IDF is basically
a sparse retrieval method,
where you have a
score function that
looks at documents and queries.
So D and Q. And then there are
basically two terms that matter.
One is the TF, the
Term Frequency.
And the other is the IDF, the
Inverse Document Frequency.
So this inverse
document frequency
is actually a really nice
idea from Karen Sparck Jones,
really underrated researcher.
She's done some amazing work.
But the basic idea
is that you want
to look at the words
that are very special.
So they don't occur in lots
of different documents.
And so the overlap between
the word "the" doesn't really
matter.
"The" occurs everywhere.
So you want to have
the special words.
So that's what TF-IDF does
in a nutshell-- it gives you
a score for document
query overlap.
And then you can do
all kinds of things
here with how you weight it.
So there's all these
weird different parameters
like this b and
things like that,
that allow you to make
it better than just
having the TF-IDF score.
So there's a couple of
tweaks you can do there.
So BM25, actually, in
case you're wondering,
stands for Best Match 25.
So I tried to discover where
does the 25 actually come from.
That's because the preceding
24 experiments failed.
So it's literally the 25th
one that seemed to work,
and that's why it's called BM25.
It's bizarre.
So this is sparse retrieval.
It's just counting words.
So you have this
massive, massive vector
of all these word occurrences.
It's sparse because
most words never occur.
So it's sort of like a vector
of vocabulary size dimensions.
So most of that
is obviously zero.
So that's actually
a nice property
if you want to do
fast search on a CPU.
Because on a CPU,
sparse dot product
is fairly easy to compute.
So this is used in the system
called DrQA, which is really
one of the first neural
instances of this open domain,
open book question
answering paradigm.
So you have a question like,
how many of Warsaw's inhabitants
blah, blah, blah.
So you want to ask
basically Wikipedia
what the answer is for this.
So then you have this
document retriever
based on these sparse--
so BM25, I think, in this case--
retrieval methods.
You pass that to this--
I think this was still
by LSTM at the time--
a document reader model.
And then that model
gives you the answer.
So this, I think, is
really the first instance
of having this separation
between a retrieval
and a generator
system that you use
for answering complicated
questions based on open domain
knowledge.
So after the sparse
stuff, there was a bunch
of work on dense retrieval.
And so the advantage
of dense retrieval--
so this is just like word
embeddings, basically vectors.
They're dense now,
no longer sparse.
So they're much smaller in
terms of dimensionality.
And the nice advantage
of dense retrieval
is that it's not really
about specific words.
So if there are
synonyms, you can still
find the relevant document,
which you couldn't really do
with a sparse representation.
So that's really the
advantage of dense
is that you get
semantic similarity.
So you can do this
over word embeddings
that doesn't really
work all that well.
But at the time that people
started thinking about this,
BERT was already out there.
And BERT is really
great for giving you
a vector representation for
an entire sequence of words.
So a sentence representation
or a passage representation.
So there are all these cool
systems like ORCA and DPR,
the Dense Passage Retriever,
where they essentially
use the retrieval as a latent
variable in the system.
And the way to get
the latent variable
to work to be good
enough, essentially
to train the entire
system is to pre-train
the retriever on
relevant information.
So for archive, they do
something called inverse close.
So they do a close
task where you
want to find passages that
are relevant to the preceding
passage.
And then DPR, they just train
it on the supervised thing.
But really, the
core idea here is
that, as you can see
in this graph here,
you can do better than BM25
if you had lots of documents.
And the way you compute the
score function is much simpler.
It's just the dot product.
So the nice thing
about dot products
is that you can do them very,
very efficiently on the GPU
as well if you know
what you're doing.
So what you really
want to get at
is Maximum Inner
Product Search, MIPS.
So this is one of the core
ideas of a lot of this stuff.
And you can do MIPS with ANN,
Approximate Nearest Neighbor
search.
And so there's this really
brilliant piece of work
out of FAIR for my
colleagues at the time
called FAISS, which
really underlies
all of these modern
vector databases.
So all the popular ones that
are of re-implementations
of this FAISS idea one is
in like Rust one, is in Go.
But it's all basically
the same idea.
It's just FAISS.
And so FAISS really powers
a lot of this stuff.
And whenever somebody
tells you something
about a vector database,
just think about FAISS.
Very fast dot product.
So, obviously, you can
go beyond dot product.
Yes.
What is it?
What's FAISS?
What is FAISS?
Yeah.
So it's an open-source library,
Facebook AI Similarity Search.
Yeah, [INAUDIBLE].
No, so it's just basically
off the shelf and algorithms.
Yeah, so there are all
kinds of different--
I don't know if you do you know
what product quantization is
and things like that.
So there are basically-- so
you have a bunch of vectors.
And you can just compute
the full dot product,
which is sort of inefficient.
So what you can do is try to
compress subspaces of the vector
and then just look at
the kind of centroids.
So you can quantize
subvectors of the full vector
and then do much faster search
over just the centroids.
It's a good question.
Any other questions?
All right, so about
this dot product idea.
So what we have
here is some people
call this a Siamese network.
I guess it is.
So you have two different
bird models or whatever
your encoder is here.
And then at the end, you
get these two vectors.
And then you just
do dot product.
So you get one single score.
But you can do all kinds
of much fancier things
if you're willing to give up
on this bi encoder approach.
So a really nice example
from one of your colleagues
here at Stanford is ColBert.
So what this does is
lay the interaction.
So instead of just having
this dot product here,
you have a more complicated
version of computing a score
where you aggregate
over maximum similarity
scores between different words.
So I only recently
actually discovered
that this is called ColBert
because of the late night show
Colbert.
So it's Omar's joke,
actually, this name.
But just so you know,
if you run into it.
But I think if we look at
where the state of the art
has been going now, one of the
nice things about these vector
databases is that
they're super efficient.
So dot product is
much more efficient
than this late
interaction stuff,
especially if you do the
approximate nearest neighbor
search.
But there's been some
really cool work.
So things like
SPLADE, they basically
have sparse meat dense in a way.
So one of the big problems
as I said with sparse
is that you can't really handle
synonyms and things like that.
But what you could do is take a
dense model like a BERT model,
look at this one word
in your sequence,
try to see which other
words fit in the same slot.
So that gives you the synonyms.
So now you can give all these
synonyms to a sparse vector.
And then you can just
do sparse dot product,
and so have a much, much more
efficient way to do search
without giving up on
all the cool stuff
that you get from a
dense representation.
So that's one thing.
And this other idea I really
like is called DRAGON.
So this, I think, is
really the best generalized
dense retriever.
So if you want to take something
off the shelf right now
and just go to Hugging
Face or something,
then this DRAGON or
DragonPlus is probably
the thing you want to
use for dense retriever.
And the way they train this is
through this progressive data
augmentation strategy to make
the model better and better
over time by sampling
very difficult negatives.
And that gives you very
good representations.
And so the other
thing about this
I think is the only final point
about retrieval in general
is that what we see happening
right now if you look
at the developer
community around RAG
is that they're all doing
hybrid search right now.
So you can actually just
combine the search results
from your sparse BM25 or
whatever thing or SPLAYED.
And you can combine
them with your DRAGON.
And then you get this ranking
that works even better.
So then you get
best of both worlds,
but then you get
all these questions
about how do you
combine the results.
Any questions on this part?
Oh, can you hear me?
Yes.
Oh, sorry.
On the earlier
slide, has there been
any work on benchmark, how much
less hallucination RAG incurs
over a closed book
question answering?
For example, directly asking
the large language model
the question, has there been any
benchmarking studies in this?
Yeah, so there's a great
paper if I can say so myself
on the fact that
retrieval augmentation
reduces hallucination.
It's from 2021, I think.
So yeah, you can just--
if you literally look for
retrieval augmentation reduces
hallucination, then
you'll find the paper.
Oh, thank you.
[INAUDIBLE],, what's
the [INAUDIBLE]??
Yeah, so very often, you want to
have very precise word overlap
for things where you don't
want to have the synonyms
or the nearest neighbors.
So if there's a brand name or
something like that, then--
let's say the brand is Apple.
You don't want to find
stuff about pears.
So that's what you would
do with a dense retriever.
So it really depends on
what you want to use it for.
That's why hybrid is
probably the way to go.
It's a good question.
Wait, with the dense things,
it's contextualized embeddings.
But shouldn't it realize
Apple, the company,
would be different from--
No, so if they were actually
contextualized, then yes.
But very often, it's a
frozen retrieval system.
That's one of the problems
with all the frozen RAG stuff.
I might be missing
something very basic here.
[INAUDIBLE] referring
to the vectors
that you're getting
the [INAUDIBLE]..
Vectors that you're using is
either the [INAUDIBLE] query
or the [INAUDIBLE].
No.
And so the document and the
query, they're the same.
So they're either
sparse, or they're dense.
So if they're sparse, the
components of the vector
are literally the other words.
So--
You just one
penalized when you're
[INAUDIBLE] to the thing
that creates the embeddings?
How are you getting [INAUDIBLE]?
So it's literally counts.
So basically, it's one big
matrix of documents as rows.
And the columns are the
words in the documents.
And then you just
count how often
a word occurs in a document.
Oh.
So that's a sparse.
[INAUDIBLE] property of sparse.
You're also referring
to [INAUDIBLE]..
Yeah, and so in
the field, we call
them sparse embeddings
or sparse retrieval
because most of that vector
is 0 because most words don't
occur in that document.
Does that make sense?
Yeah.
Cool.
So let's talk about
doing slightly better.
So going back to
Steven's question about,
OK, we have this
retrieval thing.
But how do we actually make this
retrieval good for the context
that it's going to be used in?
So can we contextualize the
retrieval for the generator,
even if it's a generator
where we might not
have access to the weights?
So it could be a GPT4 model.
We just send it to some API.
We get some stuff back.
And so one paper I really
like is called "RePlug."
So just to explain
what this looks like.
So you have this context.
You have a retriever that
we do the standard retrieval
step with.
This is a dense retriever.
Sorry.
And now you compute
the likelihood.
So you basically just
normalize the scores
that you get for
the top k documents
to get a distribution here.
And then you give each one
of the retrieved documents
separately to this generator,
to your language model.
So you can look at the
perplexity of the correct answer
for that language model.
So now we have these two
probability distributions or two
likelihoods, essentially.
And we can minimize
the kl divergence
to make sure that
we can actually
retrieve the documents
that lead to the lowest
perplexity on the right
answer for the language model.
So super simple idea.
Works really, really well.
And the nice thing about this
is completely agnostic of what
happens upstream.
So this will work for any
sort of encoder-decoder.
For any language model, what
you need is a perplexity score.
But for most
language models, you
can get that, not
necessarily all of them.
So that's one thing.
And then there's this other
really nice approach on--
Well, what parameters are
[INAUDIBLE] in the retriever?
So in the retriever,
you're literally
updating the dense
representations.
So your encoder basically for
your dense representation.
That's a good question.
We'll get into that a bit more.
So there's another paper on
in-context retrieval augmented
language models, where the
whole paper is basically
about just doing BM25 and
just giving stuff directly
to the context of
the language model.
And things work.
So it's frozen RAG but even
more primitive in a way
where the retriever is this
very old sparse algorithm.
But it works
really, really well.
But then they have this
really awesome section
where they show that you can
just have this reranker on top
of the BM25 results.
And you can backprop
into this reranker.
So now you still keep the
language model completely fixed.
So that's this part
of the loss here.
So you have a stop gradient
on the parameters theta.
That's just your language model.
But now you have
this rank function
here that you can backprop into.
So that's your
reranker is basically--
it can be a BERT model
or anything like that
works on top of the
things you initially
retrieved from your BM25.
And now you have
this BERT reranker
that you can backprop into.
So this also works
really, really nice.
So we're slowly progressing
towards having a system that
is much more optimized for being
properly retrieval augmented
in a way where it's useful
and contextualized for what
you want to use it for.
So yeah, just to point
out what that looks
like with this reranker.
So you just have this
extra step, essentially.
So we have our retriever,
then we have our reranker,
then we have our
generator and our output.
[INAUDIBLE]
No, not necessarily.
So for this one, you do, yeah.
So for RePlug, you don't.
Yeah, [INAUDIBLE].
Got it.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So basically, you need to get--
[INAUDIBLE]
Not all of them.
Some of them do.
But yeah, there are
all kinds of tricks you
can do on top of that, yeah.
So basically, the
question is, how do we get
gradients flowing into this?
So if you don't
actually have access
to the full parameters
of the model
so that you can backprop
all the way through it,
then you can do a reinforce
style loss on the retrieval.
And then you just pass
the log likelihood
if you have access to that or
some other black box function.
All right, the next
thing, you can do
is to optimize both the
retriever and the generator.
And so this really
starts getting
to the proper contextualization
of the entire architecture
where you want everything
to work together.
So rather than having
this frozen thing where
everything is
basically not aware
that the other part exists.
It's like two
halves of the brain.
They're not talking
to each other.
One is your retriever.
That is your language model.
There's no connection.
They're just sort
of like something
is thrown over the fence, and
then you hope for the best.
So instead of that, we
have everything much closer
and learning together.
So one of the first ways of
doing this with a generator
was RAG, Retrieval
Augmented Generation,
which we did at FAIR in 2020.
And it's very similar to
what we've already seen.
We basically have
this retriever here
that works over
different documents.
You get some score
function that gets
given to this generator
that generates the answer.
And now you want to
backprop all the way
and update your
generator as well.
So in the previous
two architectures,
we saw you keep the
generator fixed.
You backprop into
your retriever.
But here we update everything.
Well, not exactly
everything, as you'll see,
but we'll also update
the part of the retriever
and the generator.
So in this RAG
model, we actually
have two different
ways of doing this.
And this is probably
something that when
we talk about this, if you think
about this long enough, then
you'll think like, OK, but when
actually do I need to retrieve?
Do I retrieve every time
I generate a new token?
Or do I just retrieve
once and then generate
an entire sequence?
Or maybe I want to
retrieve every n tokens?
So these are hyperparameters.
Or maybe I want to
learn when to retrieve
as well as we'll see that's
also something people have done.
So these are two
different ways to do it.
And what we do in this
paper-- basically,
the whole point of the paper is
that this frozen thing doesn't
really work all that well.
So I think what people
call RAG now is usually
refers to the frozen thing,
but the whole paper basically
would never have been accepted
anywhere if we had just
done the frozen thing.
The whole point of the paper is
that you want to optimize it.
And so at my
company, Contextual,
we call this frozen thing
Frankenstein's monster,
because it's really
like you cobble together
these different pieces.
It's really like Frankenstein.
You just put it together,
and then it walks.
But it doesn't
really have a soul.
It doesn't really actually work.
It's not the real thing.
So that's great for
everyone here, I think,
because there are so
many opportunities
to do better than what most
people are using right now.
So one of the limitations of
the original RAG architecture
is that it only
supports a very small k.
So if you have lots
and lots of documents,
then the problem is that
you have to fit all of them
into context.
But how do you really
get that to fit?
So one thing you can do is
you first encode things so
that you get one single
representation or only
the few top-level
representations.
Then you concatenate.
Those and then you just
feed them to the decoder.
So this is FiD,
Fusion in Decoder.
And as you can see, this
scales to a much higher number
of passages, and that leads
to corresponding improvements
in the scores that
you care about.
So that's a really cool idea.
And so we're slowly
moving towards more
decoder-only architectures.
So in RAG, we have
this BART model.
It's an encoder-decoder
architecture.
But here, you just
have this decoder
that does some fancy
attention over stuff
that you retrieved before.
And so another pure decoder
language model architecture
is this one, kNN-LM,
which I think
is very elegant
in its simplicity.
So it's basically you just
have a normal language model.
But you interpolate the
normal language model weights
with things that you retrieved.
So basically, you have
some sort of prompt.
So like Obama's birthplace is.
You go to your big corpus.
You find similar things.
You look at the words that come
next to the similar things.
You rank that thing.
You sample your top k.
You renormalize that.
So now you have a
bunch of scores,
and now you can just interpolate
between your retrieved
non-parametric memory scores and
your parametric language model
scores.
So this is very late
fusion in a sense.
At the very end, you
combine these two,
and it allows you to reweight
the pure language model
probabilities or likelihoods.
So this works really well.
And it scales especially well
if you have a huge retrieval
corpus.
So if you have trillions and
trillions of tokens in there,
you can have a much
smaller language model
that does not that much heavy
lifting because you can really
rely on this big source corpus
that you're working from.
And so that idea was exploited
by this paper called "Retro"
out of DeepMind, where they
showed that you can have a 25
times smaller retrieval
augmented language model trained
from scratch.
So really pre-trained
entirely from scratch
that outperforms this
25 times bigger language
model on the same data
in terms of perplexity,
which is pretty impressive.
So this architecture
is much more efficient
than a parametric
model because you can
rely on this external memory.
So if your external
memory is big enough,
you can get pretty huge gains.
So there was a lot of
excitement about RETRO
when it was announced,
but it's a DeepMind paper.
So there's really
no open-source.
Nothing really to validate
that this actually works.
And so very recently, there has
been a bit of work from NVIDIA
called Retro++, where they have
this hybrid between the RETRO
architecture, and then
they do basically RAG.
They put the top one
or the top k results
in the context of the
language model after all.
So it's a crossover
between RAG and RETRO.
And they showed some
really nice results here.
But I think it's pointing
to this big flaw, I think,
is that, why is there still no
good open-source RETRO model?
That probably tells you
something about whether it
actually really works.
I spent a lot of
time in my career
trying to reproduce
DeepMind papers that
didn't necessarily always work.
And so I think the
same is true for RETRO.
And that's why we need
to do this in context RAG
on top of RETRO to
actually get it to work.
But could it just be
a true [INAUDIBLE]??
Because you're searching
a trillion [INAUDIBLE]??
Yeah, so--
Deploying that
[INAUDIBLE] stuff?
Yeah, so the doing retrieval
over that big corpus
is not that difficult,
actually, yeah.
So there are even like
distributed FAISS packages.
You can just do
everything yourself.
So--
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, so in terms
of compute, it's
actually not that hard
anymore to reproduce something
like this.
But I tried several times, and
it is not really reproducible.
So the only way
to get it to work
is if you do this in context
RAG on top of the RETRO thing.
And then as you can see
here in the results,
then it actually gives you a
gain over the pure GPT model.
So it starts from
a GPT, and then
they retrofit as they
call it the GPT model.
So in short, I think
there are still
a lot of work to be done in
pre-training these systems
really from scratch.
And RETRO showed that
it might be possible,
but we don't necessarily
know exactly how
to do it the right way.
And this is really one of the
interesting open questions.
Any questions on that?
Online?
No?
OK, then we'll move on.
So let's go all the way
with the contextualization.
So with RETRO and with RAG,
what we actually did is
we only updated
the query encoder.
So updating the document
encoder is very expensive.
So one of the first
papers, actually,
the OG of the non-frozen dense
retrieval augmented methods,
is this paper called "REALM."
This is really like
visionary work.
This was basically the first
version that did this properly
where they updated
it all the way,
including the document encoder.
So can someone
explain to me why it's
expensive to update
the document encoder?
So let's say we have a
trillion tokens in our corpus.
So now we go all the way.
So we basically
do a forward pass.
We get a gradient at the end.
Now we back propagate the
gradient through the retriever.
We update the query encoder.
Now we have to update
the document encoder.
So what do we then
need to do after we've
updated the document encoder?
We need to re-encode
the entire internet.
So basically, every
single gradient update,
we have to re-encode
whatever our index is.
And so if this is like
trillions of tokens,
it's like re-encoding the
internet after every batch
update.
So that's not very efficient.
[INAUDIBLE] or other stuff
that if you [INAUDIBLE]
take care of all the activations
and have some [INAUDIBLE]
unpredictable thing.
So [INAUDIBLE] this?
Yeah.
Yeah, that's one way to do it.
So there are a bunch
of different ways
to update the document encoder.
So what they do in REALM is they
basically do it for t batches.
Then they stop.
They re-encode the
entire internet,
and then they train again.
So it's sort of
asynchronous updates.
They have this very fancy
sharding mechanisms,
where they take down certain
parts of their entire index
and then update them on the fly.
So you can do it.
It's just very expensive.
So one of the things
that a lot of people
have been thinking about,
not exactly the LoRa idea,
but similar versions of
that are around like,
can you make it more
efficient so that you don't
have to do this asynchronously?
So one of the downsides
of this REALM architecture
is that it's really
just a bird model,
but then you do this
retrieval augmentation
on a bird model with
other bird models.
So it's not really generative.
It's not really gen AI
in the modern paradigm.
But if you want to read
one paper on this topic,
this is a very good one to read.
The other one that is really,
really good to read is this
paper called "Atlas."
So Atlas is-- so this is out
of FAIR with a bunch of folks,
the folks who did RAG and the
folks who did FID and really
a brilliant set of people.
And this is really a
comprehensive analysis
of everything that's happening
in this architecture.
So the first question
they really look at
is, how do we train
this retriever?
So we've seen a couple
of versions of this,
but which one
actually works better?
They haven't really
been compared
in a head-to-head setting.
So one thing is we have this FID
style attention distillation.
So that's really too complicated
to go into detail here.
But the others are
actually very simple.
So one is this loss we've
basically seen before.
So we've seen this, I think,
with the in-context RAG one.
So we have a stop gradient
on the language model,
and then we update
the retriever.
The other one is what
we've seen with REPLUG.
So this is basically
exactly the REPLUG loss.
So we have the KL
divergence of the documents
and the improvement that you see
when you give it that document.
The other thing they
have is basically
the inverse of that one.
So if I take this
one document out,
how does that
affect my perplexity
of the language model?
And so this one, I think,
is actually quite elegant
because that really
gets to how valuable
is this one single
document for me answering
this question correctly.
So they compare all of
these different versions.
And what you can see is that the
REPLUG-style loss and this leave
one out loss, they
performed a lot better
than all of these others.
So this fixed retriever or
no joint pre-training, these
are really the baseline frozen
RAG models or close book.
And as you can see, you
can do really a lot better
if you optimize things.
And so just leave one out
thing is probably the best,
I would say.
So then the other question
is, how do you actually
train that entire system?
What data or what tasks
do you train this on?
So they also experiment with
a bunch of different versions.
So one is doing PrefixLM, if
you're familiar with that.
So they basically take a
chunk that occurs somewhere
on the internet, and then
they predict the next chunk
from that chunk.
So it's really like
sentence to sentence.
So maybe like Skip-Thought
back in the day,
but now you have this
retrieval step where
you predict the next sentence.
And then they just do
T5 styles or denoising.
So there's mass
language modeling
if you're familiar with T5.
And then they have this title
to section generation piece.
So I think the takeaway
from this table
is basically that
whatever you do here--
so they're using T5 models.
So whatever you do here needs to
be the same that your language
model expects.
So for T5, that's T5 style loss.
And then the next final
question that they
look into going back to what
we talked about, how exactly do
we update this retriever?
So do we have to update
the document encoder?
Or do we maybe have
to do some reranking?
Or do we maybe just
update the query?
And quite surprisingly,
I think they find
that just updating the query.
So in the original
RAG paper, it's
actually already basically
good enough in many cases.
So that's nice because
it's much more efficient
if you don't have to update
your documents all the time.
I think the real question
here, though, is like,
how good is your document
representation to begin with?
So you need to have very, very
high quality embedding model
for this to work.
If you don't have that,
then this will not work.
But if you do have that, then
you get a very nice query side
fine-tuning thing.
What's [INAUDIBLE]?
So the Atlas paper is about
trying to do few shot language
modeling tasks.
So it's how many examples
are given in the context.
Yeah, so the main
takeaway here is
that if you compare
the close book,
equivalent model to the
retrieval augmented model,
you see very big improvements.
That's really the only takeaway
of this entire section.
But I think that that's
really saying something
in terms of what we
should be thinking about.
How much time do
I have in total?
There's still plenty of time.
OK, OK.
I think.
All right.
Other questions?
Yeah, other documents
in the training
set same as [INAUDIBLE] when you
change the setup [INAUDIBLE]??
Yeah, so they can be different.
So in Atlas, Atlas
basically tries everything.
So they also try to
see, what happens
if I train this on Wikipedia,
but I swap in a common crawl
index?
And I think-- so in Atlas but
also in RETRO, the main finding
is just the more, the better.
So it's really just like
the bigger your index,
the more likely you are to
find the exact right thing
and then make the
right prediction.
Any other questions on this?
Oh, yeah.
Sorry, this is a question about
the generator in, I guess,
the RAG system.
So recently, I saw a
paper on Mistral 7B.
So it introduces a lot of
these new architectural changes
like the sliding
window attention
to handle longer sequences at a
smaller cost and the group query
attention for faster inference.
I'd like to know your thoughts
on designing a generator
specifically for RAG
leveraging, for example,
where Mistral 7B currently
is because, for example,
the sliding window attention,
I could see how that could be
adapted to the RAG case.
Yeah, so maybe your read on
what makes Mistrals special
is a bit different from mine.
So I don't think that the
sliding attention window thing
is actually that interesting.
The reason Mistral works
so well is because it's
trained on a lot of data.
And you can do that more
efficiently because you
have sliding window attention.
So you don't need to
attend to everything.
So to answer your question--
I guess you're asking about the
architecture of the generator
if you know that there's
going to be a retriever.
So I think that's basically
what RETRO tried to do.
Actually, some of the
people on the RETRO paper
are at Mistral now.
So they have this chunk
cross-attention idea here.
So you basically have
a language model,
but the way it does
attention over the things
you retrieve in your
RETRO architecture.
They get integrated
into a model,
not using the standard
attention mechanism,
but using this slightly
different chunk cross-attention.
OK, so I think the
sliding window attention
point I was trying to get at was
that it uses a fixed window so
that whenever you're doing
the query key computation
with the query vectors
and the key vectors,
you're using a fixed
window attention.
So I think my idea
was to actually, one,
use a dynamic window.
Because for example,
the RAG case,
if you use a fixed window
when you're doing attention,
it is possible that you
actually are leaving--
you're only looking at a
fixed span of information.
So if you could
maybe adapt Mistral
so that you could make it
better for the RAG case
in, for example,
making the fixed window
size the dynamic window.
Yeah.
Yeah, I think it's
an interesting idea.
So for me, what Mistral is
doing with the sliding window,
that's basically like a ConvNet.
So we had all these
convolutional-- light ConvNets,
where we would have
word embeddings,
and you would do convolutions
over it and then pull.
And then you would still
get the information out.
So it's not that the
sliding window prohibits you
from looking earlier.
It's just that happens higher
up in your transformer, sort of.
Yeah, yeah.
OK.
So I think that definitely
is an interesting direction
to think in, yeah.
Yeah, so I think it's
not too crazy to say,
are there any
architectural changes
that we can introduce into
this 7 billion parameter models
so that they could be better
adapted to the RAG case?
Yeah, so there might be.
Yeah, I think one question
is just, How do you--
how do you do the attention
over things you've retrieved?
which I think is what you're--
Yeah, thanks.
So just to make
sure I understand.
So I mean, in this RETRO model,
you are retrieving each block.
And when you talk about putting
the retrieval in the context,
are you saying that you
only do it at the beginning,
and you don't do
it at each block?
Yeah, so in context--
so this is-- it's not
exactly every layer, sort of.
So it's every token.
So every step, basically,
not every block.
So it doesn't make sense.
So it's not every layer
that you do the retrieval.
Yeah, so every step.
So this is kind of
like what RAG token is.
So you retrieve every token.
So you generate, and then
you can retrieve again.
Or in the case of retro,
you, can generate a chunk,
and then you retrieve
chunks again.
If you look at the
in-context case,
you retrieve once at the
beginning, and then you give it.
So [INAUDIBLE],,
you're saying that
doing this multiple
retrieval, [INAUDIBLE]..
Yeah, so the in-context thing--
so here, you don't actually
give it as context at all
directly to the model.
So here, you let the
decoder attend over it.
Like computation.
Yeah.
And that nobody [INAUDIBLE].
So I don't think cross-attention
really works, yeah.
Other questions?
Deep inside that in some cases,
the training of the retriever
is not so necessary
because a large lost.
So I'm wondering your
insights of the cases.
Like what cases are
really necessarily need
to asynchronous update or
any updates or documents?
Yeah.
So you do want to update
the retriever, right?
But only part of
the retriever is
necessary to be updated
for a lot of these cases.
But so I think it--
so these are very
specific data sets, right?
Natural questions, wizard
of Wikipedia and fever,
so they're really very
knowledge-intensive tasks.
So in that case, if you already
have a very good system like DPR
that is specifically
pre-trained for those tasks,
then you only need to
update the query encoder.
So I would expect
that if you move
beyond this to general language
modeling things like retro
then you probably do want
to update the document
encoder at least in a way
where you can scale it.
So everything that's in this
task is very knowledge-intensive
and actually decouples
the [INAUDIBLE]
and the generator
[INAUDIBLE] as long
as we have a good
knowledge of the documents
by those good
models [INAUDIBLE]..
Yeah.
But so you need to learn how
to query into that index.
So if you don't do
that, then yeah,
you don't get really
good performance.
So that's like your closed
book performance, right?
If you just have the language
model and you're just like,
what does the parametric
model on its own
without the retrieval?
What does it actually know?
As you can see, they're
pretty big gaps there.
Other questions?
Otherwise I will
cover other questions.
No?
Hello?
Yeah.
Go for it.
Oh.
Quick question.
So what about more
theoretical retrieval?
Like I suppose
there'll be message
trying to not just
retrieve a single chunk
but some groups of
chunks or something
or summarized versions.
There's been some interesting
work on doing that where
you first try to find.
So you can have multiple
indices and they can cascade.
So first, you want to find
the relevant document.
So you have some
document representation.
And then within
that document, you
want to find the relevant chunk,
so you can do that direction.
You can also do it in reverse.
I think I have
something on the slide
there where you
can find the chunk
and then expand the
context around it
and then give that to
the language model.
And so I think--
yeah, there are all kinds
of interesting things
you can do there.
Cool.
Thanks.
I guess another thing,
just like can you
compare RAG versus like
long context efforts.
So there are lots of things
like around just having
really long context and the
extreme, it could replace RAG.
But I don't know, like
give me your takes.
Yeah.
So everybody understands
this question, right?
So there's a trend where we
want to have very long context
language models so
that basically you
can take Harry Potter
or something just put it
in the context and then
ask a question like what
is the name of like Harry
Potter's owl or something.
And then it can just attend
over the entire thing.
So attending over
all of Harry Potter
to answer that one question
is super inefficient, right?
So most of Harry Potter has
nothing to do with the owl.
So but you are still
reading it if you do it
with the long context window.
So that's why I think doing
it the right way where
you have this nonparametric
component is a much more
efficient way to
solve this problem.
And if you actually look at
the literature on long context
windows, the way they solve
the problem of scaling
the attention mechanism is
by making it very sparse.
So they're basically
turning it--
so that's a different
kind of sparse,
but they're turning it into a
non-parametric retrieval problem
behind-the-scenes.
They're not actually
all that different.
If you want to
scale long context,
then you're going to
move towards a RAG style
architecture.
Good.
Thanks.
All right.
So let's talk about some
other interesting questions.
So one thing and
I already alluded
to this is when do
we actually retrieve?
So if we're doing-- if we
want to retrieve every token,
that's also very inefficient
because I probably don't have
to retrieve to generate the--
right?
I can probably do that on my
own with a language model.
It's a waste to go
and retrieve stuff.
But if I only retrieve once at
the beginning of the sequence,
that's probably also not great.
So what we ideally want to
be able to do is to say,
OK, sometimes, I
want to retrieve,
sometimes, I don't
want to retrieve.
And I'm going to
learn when I want
to expand the compute budget
on doing the retrieval.
So a nice paper where
they have a stab at this
is called FLARE for active
retrieval augmentation
where they basically have
the language model decide
when it should do a search and
what it should do to search for.
So I think this fits
in a general trend
that you can see in the
field around agents.
So we can talk a little
bit more about that too.
So this other
question that I think
we also covered already here is
how do we train this at scale?
So we can do these
asynchronous updates.
We can do rerankers.
We can do query side only.
There's this really
nice paper which
is quite close I think to
the idea you proposed where
you first use BM25 to create a
batch basically where everything
is very similar in terms
of what you retrieved
and now you have
this in-batch update.
So it's like a reranker where
you encode the information that
is just in your batch
using this other model
and now you can update
this model on the fly,
so you don't have to
worry too much about doing
the full document side update.
And again, here,
what really matters
is like how big is your index.
If you have an
amazing index, you
can basically solve any
problem just by looking it up.
So rather than cramming
it into your parameters,
you can just find it.
This is a really nice
paper called SILO.
So one of the
interesting things I
think that's going to happen
in the next year or two
around language models is there,
and you've seen this already
there's a bunch of
lawsuits against OpenAI
and other places around where
does the data exactly come from.
So one very elegant
solution I think
is to have a system
that you train
on data that is safe so you can
train that thing on Wikipedia.
But now during test
time, you can give it
a data store that has
maybe slightly riskier
information in it so
this massive index
of all the stuff on the internet
including some things that
are maybe higher risk.
You can still have them in your
index but your language model,
your retrieval augmented
language model, I should say,
you know that that thing is
safe because it was trained
on data that is public domain.
So that's what they do
in SILO and they show
that that works really well.
So that's one possible solution
to a lot of the compliance
and legal risk around
language model deployments.
There's a great paper
on also from one
of your colleagues
around context
getting lost in the middle.
I think this is also a
fascinating phenomenon.
This is on a frozen RAG system.
But language models are very
similar to humans in what things
they pay attention to.
So if you give them a bunch
of things that you retrieve,
what they will look at are
the first things you list
and the last things you list.
And they will ignore the middle.
And so if it actually
respected the rank function,
then this curve would go
down all the way, right?
But it goes up.
So I think that's a very
interesting observation which
shows that how brittle
these systems can be.
So if you have a
frozen RAG system,
it can be very,
very brittle where
like the order of
the retrieve context
matters a lot in whether you
get the right answer or not.
Can you then work on reading
this as a reinforcement learning
problem in a sense
of place and vector
as opposed to specifically
going for interpretation,
try to output a vector
that's going to inner product
with just the right--
maybe you can tune for
a particular database?
Yeah.
I don't know exactly.
So what I just described
somebody asked,
like how do you
actually-- so I said
there are other ways to do this
and then the question was how
do you do that?
So the way you do that
is using reinforce.
So yeah, there has been
work on doing that.
So some of the older papers
were playing with this.
But one of the big
problems with--
so I think the
REPLUG solution is
more elegant for
solving that problem
because you actually use
signal from the language model.
And if you just do reinforce,
it's very high variance.
So you're it's going to be
super finicky if you don't
want to destroy your index.
But people have tried it, yeah.
So there are some really
nice work from OpenAI
where they basically show--
and again, we're like thinking
more and more about agents here,
right?
Where they show something very
similar to the FLARE results
from earlier with
active retrieval
that doesn't necessarily have
to be some index that you own.
It can be just some
web search, right?
And obviously in this
case, you don't really
have access to the web
search necessarily, so Bing
or whatever they use here is not
going to update its parameters.
But I just wanted to
put this in your mind,
like this is another
thing you can do, right?
And if we take this really
to the general form,
then you can think of language
models as just tool users.
So rather than just retrieval
augmenting language models,
we can tool augment language
models and retrieval is just
one of the many tools that
language models have access to.
We can have rerankers
and things on top
of the outputs of these tools.
And so one of the big
questions, I think,
is, how do you actually get this
system to learn stuff, right?
So we're going to need RL if we
want this system to really learn
how to take these
actions properly.
And so yeah, this has
been taken to the extreme
and is self RAG architecture
where they have this retrieval
step and it's active and
then you criticize it
and then you basically do some
natural language inference
and all of that just
with one language model
to answer the questions.
So the other missing
piece-- so I'm just
going through a bunch
of open questions
that people have
looked at but feel
free to interrupt me if there's
anything you want to know.
But so instruction
tuning, we established
at the beginning of
the lecture that this
is pretty important for
getting things to work, so
fixing the user interface.
But the instruction
tuning has almost always
only happened on
the language model
and not on the entire system.
So I think one of the
interesting things
that people are looking at
now with things like raw data
and InstructRetro is how can
we instruct and fine tune
an entire retrieval
augmented system.
So all the way into
the retrieval step
can we generate
data so that also
follows the
instructions properly
which currently doesn't
happen in any of these model
architectures.
And then finally, I
think I would be remiss
if I didn't really talk about
what people call advanced RAGs.
So like the developer
community has been really doing
some awesome stuff,
so like frameworks,
like LlamaIndex, and LangChain.
And there's all these open
source vector databases
like Chroma and Weaviate.
And they're all about
making RAGs really easy.
But this is all
frozen RAG, right?
But even with frozen RAG, you
can really do incredible things.
So we mentioned some
of these already.
So child-parent
recursive retriever.
So you find small parts and then
you give the big parts around it
to the language model.
You can do hybrid search where
we use reciprocal rank fusion,
so we have different
search results
that we didn't combine before
we give the final thing
to the language model.
There's zero shot like large
language model reranker,
so basically the
score function is
not-- doesn't come
from your retrieval,
it comes directly from
the language model.
And then hypothetical document
embeddings which I think
is a really cool idea.
So you just basically
you fix hallucination
through hallucination.
So you get a
question, then you let
the language model hallucinate
a bunch of possible answers,
then you go and search
for nearest neighbors
to the possible answers, and
you give those as context
and then it gives the
right answer based on that.
So it was really like
hallucinating answers.
And I think it's a
brilliant solution.
So there's a lot
of stuff happening
in the frozen RAG
community too that I think
is very interesting to look at.
So just to wrap up, looking
at the future of this stuff.
There are still lots of very
interesting open questions.
So if you're a student thinking
about how to solve any of these,
I think you can have
quite a lot of impact.
So how exactly do we
do like pre-training
of this architecture?
And do we even
need to pre-train?
I think even retro shows
that you don't necessarily
have to pre-train,
so but maybe there's
something wrong
with how we do that.
What do scaling laws look like?
So I think there's a really
interesting question here around
if I have a huge index and
a very rich encoder of all
the information in that
index, maybe I can move,
so basically decouple all the
memorization to this index.
So I have a language model
that doesn't know anything,
it just speaks English, it
just reasons on top of it.
It has no knowledge
because that always
comes from this retriever.
If you can do
something like that,
then you get very interesting
scaling trade offs, right?
So you can have a
tiny language model
and do your retrieval to do
a lot of the heavy lifting
with your retrieval which
is nice because that's
a cached computation, right?
So you can just-- you
already have the embeddings,
you just need to
do the dot product,
so it's much more efficient than
self-attention in the language
model.
Can we move beyond by encoders?
So vector databases,
I like people
who build vector
databases, but I'm not sure
how long we're going to
keep vector databases.
Because I think reranker is
probably work just as well.
And BM25 is much more efficient
than a vector database.
So I don't really see why we
need dedicated vector databases.
And so what we're
seeing but maybe
this is a bit of a critique of
maybe Silicon Valley investment
strategies and things
like that, but a lot
of these vector
database companies
are basically becoming
database companies now.
So they are adding
all this spark stuff
because the dense
thing is not enough.
And as it turns out, there are
a lot of pretty good sparse
databases out there already like
Postgres and things like that.
And they're also all adding
vectors to their databases
so I think that's all going
to coalesce into databases.
[INAUDIBLE]
So I think there are
some interesting things
to look at for the data.
So alluding to this
instruction problem,
can we generate much better
data for training RAG systems
synthetically?
And then I think there's
this massive open question
around how we actually measure
whether the system is any good.
So right now, we just look
at downstream performance
which is OK.
But if you mess
up the retrieval,
it's very hard to measure.
But how to measure
whether your retrieval is
right is also very
difficult. So there
are some frameworks
where they try
to take like the harmonic
mean of your retrieval
accuracy and your
language model accuracy.
But I think those are also very
shoddy because we don't really
have very good data
sets to measure that on.
So I think that's a very cool
problem to work on as well.
So the other problem
that I personally
am always very excited
about is multi-modality.
And so why would we stop with
RAG systems with just text?
Right?
So you can do the same
thing with images.
You can augment language
models with vision.
So we did this
work on LENS where
we have a language
model enhanced
to see where you can just give
a computer vision pipeline just
like a retrieval pipeline and
give that to a frozen language
model and pass it
through the context
and that system actually is
an amazing visual question
answering system.
It's close to state-of-the-art
flamingo from DeepMind which is
also very hard to reproduce
because there's no open source
version of that.
So we've done some early
work on this in 2021
where we have this
cross-modal retrieval
and there are some more recent
work out of fair where they also
look at this.
So I think that's
really like, if you
look at the trend in the field
like multi-modality with GPT 4
and things like that
is really a hot topic.
So everything is going
in that direction.
So it's an interesting
thing to think about.
So overall, I think
it would be nice
if everybody moves away from
RAG 1.0 to frozen Frankenstein
RAG and moves towards this
much more optimized version RAG
2.0, so it's really about
systems over models.
It's not just your language
model and your retriever
and they're separate.
It's about thinking
from a systems
perspective about the
entire thing and the problem
you're trying to solve.
And so I think that really is
the way that in deep learning
things have always
progressed, where
if you optimize the
system end-to-end,
that's always going to win out.
Like back in the day in
computer vision or NLP,
we have parsers and scene
parsers and all this stuff,
and all of that just
doesn't exist anymore now
because we optimize
the system end to end.
So that's what's going
to happen here too.
So if we take that to the
extreme, like versus chunker
thing in your documents, like
cutting it up into pieces,
you could backprop into that.
Why not?
Somebody should really do that.
So I think like trading off
costs and quality and zero shot
domain generalization,
that's really where
this stuff is going to come in.
So language models, right
now, they're amazing.
But very often, they're way too
expensive for being deployed
somewhere where you can
actually make money from them
if you're in a company.
So what you want to do is
make it much more efficient
and have the right
cost quality trade off.
And the easiest
way I can think of
is to do it through
retrieval augmentation.
But obviously, I'm very biased.
So yeah, that was
all I had actually.
So if you're interested
in this, I'm at Stanford.
So I can work with you
on research projects
on these topics or
if you want, you
can also join Contextual because
we work on this stuff every day.
Thank you.
Well, sorry, I had a
question from earlier.
Yeah.
I think you said
something really,
really I think really super
helpful earlier about Mistral
7b.
You talked about-- you compared
the sliding window attention
to convolutional
neural networks.
And I do see the
parallel because
with convolutional
neural networks
you have several layers of--
several different layers
of convolutional layers.
And the top
convolutional layers are
able to see a larger
receptive field
in the bottom
convolutional layers.
And with convolutional
layers, you're
able to tune the filter
sizes and the stride,
so you're able to see a
different receptive field.
And I was wondering if you
could see that same innovation
in Mistral 7b by tuning--
because you have different
transformer layers,
and each transformer
layer will have a span
over a different set of tokens.
And if you can tune, I guess
the transformer architecture,
the way you tune those
convolutional layers the filter
sizes the receptive
field, perhaps
we can do some optimization
in the transformer realm
that we have already done
in convolutional layers.
Yeah.
I think that-- so
that's a good idea.
There's a great paper
on light convolutions,
I think, from Michael
Auli and David Grangier
and a bunch of people,
where it's basically--
this came out at exactly the
same time as the transformer,
and the transformer is
likely more optimized
for GPU computation.
But the convolutional model
was actually slightly better
than the transformer.
It's definitely worth exploring.
OK, cool, thanks.
The advantages of the
reranker were implied.
But does that give us
a lot of the advantages
of the semantic search?
Or is the trade not that great?
Yeah.
So it depends on the problem.
I think what you
probably want to do
is cast a wide net with BM25
and then just narrow it down
with dense search.
So you often see that
as a two-stage process
where the first one is noisy.
You can add noise
actually to your retrieval
and then you use the dense
one to filter it down.
Yeah.
Everyone's trying to
maybe adapt their models
to own domain specific areas.
Like I think there are mainly
two ways to approach it.
One way is to use construction
through many things
like learning way or fine
tuning like tuning method.
And another way is just the
main topic of this lecture
is using visual automatic way.
So I'm wondering besides the low
cost advantage of the retrieval
automatic way.
Do you think that our
capacity or the quality
of visual augmented way can be
matched with those two context
learning?
Yeah.
So I think actually what's going
to happen is that all of this
will come together, right?
So if you actually train things
like end-to-end RAG 2.0 style,
then you can also fine tune
that system on some use case
end-to-end, right?
So why would you just take
the retrieval augmented system
if you can also fine tune it
on the thing you care about.
So I think in the
end, everybody's
going to do all of those things.
And then there's questions like
how do you do that efficiently,
so that's why you would use
adapters or things like that.
If there was another question.
Just about hardware,
you say it's
going to be a database thing.
But what about retrieval
hardware and you
smile because you've got so
much of the running part.
But what about--
because this is huge--
Yeah.
Trillions.
So you have any ideas?
It's just a database problem--
So I don't know if I'm allowed
to say this exactly actually.
But so one of the biggest
chip manufacturers
that recently-- their
stock has done really well,
they have some dedicated
retrieval hardware coming out
I think soon or it
might already be out.
So yeah.
Very efficient dense retrieval
is a very big business.
Other questions?
What we think
everything solving RAG
that will solve
those [INAUDIBLE]..
Yes.
I think so if you take
it to the extreme.
So one of the big
problems right now is
that if you contextualize an
existing language model that
already hallucinates,
then it's going
to be hard to get rid of
the hallucination, right?
So if you do REPLUG on GPT 4,
GPT 4 might still hallucinate.
So it could
basically just ignore
all the stuff you've
retrieved and just do
whatever it wants anyway.
So that's one of the
reasons why you want
to train the system end-to-end.
And if you take that to the
extreme where like I said,
right?
If you can just have the
language model only reasoning
and speak so it knows
English and reasoning
but it has no knowledge which
all comes from somewhere else,
then you can't hallucinate.
So it's really all grounded
in whatever is in your index.
But so they're--
about hallucination,
I'm frustrated that a lot
of people in the field
misunderstand what
hallucination even means.
So a lot of people are
conflating hallucination
with correctness
or incorrectness.
So they're like, oh, the model
made a mistake, it hallucinated.
It's like, no, it
made a mistake.
That's different
from hallucination.
Hallucination, I think,
is a very specific
retrieved something
so I have some sort
of counterfactual ground truth.
And what I'm saying does not
correspond to that ground truth.
And so yeah, I think there's a
bunch of folks at Stanford also
working on better
measurement of hallucination
and definitions and
things like that.
If I'm understanding correctly
your definition of hallucination
only makes sense in a
context with ground truth.
Yeah.
Of some ground truth, right?
So hallucination is
really like-- there is
something that is true, right?
So if we're talking
about like hallucination,
and yeah, so if we're talking
about just general parametric
language models then
the ground truth
is whatever we
consider to be true.
Right?
But we had to work for
like language models
making mistakes before it
was called making mistakes.
Yeah, on the ground,
I guess, you're
solving the housemates question
[INAUDIBLE] on that path.
Are you working on
ground truth per se
in a document saying Obama
I've never been a president
and everything falls apart.
Are you saying work
on that on this trial?
Yeah.
So I like the SILO
mentioned there as well.
So I think the whole
point is that you
can have different indices and
different definitions of ground
truth.
And so I think you could say
I only trust archive or I
only trust like peer-reviewed
papers and not just archive.
So you can make decisions
in your architecture
during test time about what
you define as ground truth.
And I also think actually that
and there's a bunch of work
I think happening
on this right now.
You can control for
how grounded you want
to be in your ground truth.
So that's another
kind of misconception
about hallucinations.
Like sometimes hallucinations
are actually good.
If you have a creative
writing assistant
and you wanted to come up
with some cool new ideas,
you want the language
model to hallucinate.
So I think what you want to
have is a tunable knob where
you say like now
you can hallucinate
and now maybe you should like
really tell me the truth on.
Anything else?
But as [INAUDIBLE] temperatures
gain, some form of control--
Yeah.
Hallucination.
So but the temperature,
that's just about
how you sample, right?
So how flat your distribution,
is that you sample from.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
Yes.
So even if you have
a low temperature,
it can still come up
with random stuff, right?
So it just says that then
you're very likely to do
like greedy sampling.
So I think what you want
to get at is something
more sophisticated than that.
Great.
Lots of interesting question.
Yeah.
I like their question.
Thanks, Douwe, again,
for the great talk.
[INAUDIBLE]